Sipper mss., 1973-2010 LMC 2354
Lilly Library
Sipper mss.
1973-2010
Lilly Library
Sipper, Ralph B.
LMC 2354
20 Boxes
The Sipper mss., 1973-2010, consists of the correspondence and business records of Ralph Bruno Sipper, 1932-, an antiquarian bookseller specializing in modern first editions.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired: 1997, 2007-2010
Biographical Note
Ralph Bruno Sipper, 1932-, of Santa Barbara, California, is one of the leading antiquarian booksellers in America specializing in modern first editions. In 1970 Sipper founded Joseph the Provider/Books in San Francisco and from that time issued sales catalogues of modern first editions that went to institutional and private collectors. He also exhibited at book fairs, appraised collections, and represented archives that were acquired by university libraries. In 1996 the Joseph the Provider Corporation was dissolved and Sipper continued selling books under his own name.
Scope and Contents
Correspondents include: Eric Ambler, Donald Barthelme, Samuel Beckett, Thomas Berger, Kay Boyle, Bill Bradley, Matthew Bruccoli, Charles Bukowski, Carter Burden, Even Connell, Jerome Cheryn, Robert Coover, William Oliver Everson, Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Giselle Freund, William Gaddis, Allen Ginsberg, William Golding, James Laughlin, Norman Mailer, John McPhee, William Meredith, Kenneth Millar, Dmitri Nabokov, Joyce Carol Oates, Robert Parker, Lawrence Clark Powell, Julian Symons, John Updike, Diane Wakoski, Eudora Welty, and Calder Willingham.
Also present are published book reviews and critical essays composed by Sipper over five decades.
Additionally there are materials pertaining to Inward Journey, a 1984 collection of memorial essays about crime fiction novelist Ross Macdonald (pen-name of Kenneth Millar, 1915-1983), edited by Ralph B. Sipper. Materials include correspondence, contract agreements, original manuscripts, galleys, photographs, congratulatory letters, and reviews. Correspondents include: Kingsley Amis; Samuel Beckett; Kay Boyle; Ray Bradbury; Raymond Carver; Don DeLillo; John Fowles; Dick Francis; David Hare; John Le Carre; Ursula LeGuin; John D. MacDonald; Norman Mailer; Alice Munro; Robert Parker; Walker Percy; Paul Theroux; and John Updike.
Related Materials
See Vonnegut mss., Corman mss. III, and Joseph the Provider mss., also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana. Books that Sipper has written or edited are catalogued in IUCAT.
Booksellers and bookselling --California.; Booksellers and bookselling; Sipper, Ralph B.; Sipper, Ralph B. --Correspondence.; Ambler, Eric, 1909-1998 --Correspondence.; Buckley, Christopher, 1948- --Correspondence.; Coover, Robert --Correspondence.; Doctorow, E. L., 1931-2015 --Correspondence.; Updike, John --Correspondence.; Easton, Robert Olney --Correspondence.; Wakoski, Diane --Correspondence.; Everson, William, 1912-1994 --Correspondence.; Gaddis, William, 1922-1998 --Correspondence.; Gallagher, Tess --Correspondence.; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997 --Correspondence.; Gold, Herbert, 1924- --Correspondence.; Jackson, Laura (Riding), 1901-1991 --Correspondence.; Laughlin, James, 1914-1997 --Correspondence.; Mailer, Norman --Correspondence.; Oates, Joyce Carol, 1938- --Correspondence.; Welty, Eudora, 1909-2001 --Correspondence.; Nabokov, Dmitri --Correspondence.
- Sipper mss., 1973-2010
  - 1997 Correspondence A-G (Box 1)
  - 1997 Correspondence H-N (Box 1)
  - 1997 Correspondence O-Z (Box 1)
  - Books Bought 1997 (Box 1)
  - Books Sold 1997 (Box 1)
  - 1998 Correspondence A-D (Box 1)
  - 1998 Correspondence E-K (Box 1)
  - 1998 Correspondence L-Z (Box 1)
  - Business Records (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Paid Invoices 1998 (Box 1)
  - Books Bought (Box 1)
  - Accounting (Box 1)
  - Advertising (Box 1)
  - Paid Invoices 1998 (Box 1)
  - Books Bought (Box 1)
  - Accounting (Box 1)
  - Advertising (Box 1)
  - Book Fairs (Box 1)
  - Car (Box 1)
  - Computering (Box 1)
  - Dues and Subscriptions (Box 1)
  - Framing and Restoration (Box 1)
  - Gifts (Box 1)
  - Office Equipment (Box 1)
  - Office Supplies (Box 1)
  - Postage (Box 1)
  - Painting (Box 1)
  - Repairs (Box 1)
  - Telephone (Box 1)
  - Travel (Box 1)
  - Utilities (Box 1)
  - Magazines (Box 1)
  - 1999 Correspondence A-E (Box 1)
  - 1999 Correspondence F-M (Box 1)
  - 1999 Correspondence N-Z (Box 2)
  - Books Sold (Box 2)
  - Business Records (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 2000 A-G (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 2000 H-O (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 2000 P-Z (Box 2)
  - Books Bought (Box 2)
  - Books Sold (Box 2)
  - Book Fairs (Box 2)
  - Accounting (Box 2)
  - Advertising (Box 2)
  - Car (Box 2)
  - Dues and Subscriptions (Box 2)
  - Entertainment (Box 2)
  - Gifts (Box 2)
  - Janitorial and Repairs (Box 2)
  - Office Supplies (Box 2)
  - Postage (Box 2)
  - Printing (Box 2)
  - Restoration (Box 2)
  - Security System (Box 2)
  - Telephone (Box 2)
  - Travel (Box 2)
  - Utilities (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 2001 A-C (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 2001 D-L (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 2001 M-R (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 2001 S-Z (Box 2)
  - Books Bought (Box 2)
  - Catalogs (Box 2)
  - Accounting (Box 3)
  - Advertising (Box 3)
  - Book Fairs (Box 3)
  - Car (Box 3)
  - Dues and Subscriptions (Box 3)
  - Janitorial and Repairs (Box 3)
  - Office Supplies (Box 3)
  - Postage (Box 3)
  - Printing (Box 3)
  - 2002 Correspondence A-E (Box 3)
  - 2002 Correspondence F-Z (Box 3)
  - 2002 Books Bought (Box 3)
  - 2002 Books Sold (Box 3)
  - Office Supplies (Box 3)
  - Gifts (Box 3)
  - Dues and Subscriptions (Box 3)
  - Business Documents (Box 3)
  - Book Fairs (Box 3)
  - Advertising (Box 3)
  - Accounting (Box 3)
  - Business Documents (Box 3)
  - Book Fairs (Box 3)
  - Advertising (Box 3)
  - Accounting (Box 3)
  - Travel (Box 3)
  - Entertainment (Box 3)
  - Car (Box 3)
  - Utilities (Box 3)
  - Security System (Box 3)
  - Restoration (Box 3)
  - Painting (Box 3)
  - Postage (Box 3)
  - 2003 Correspondence A-F (Box 3)
  - 2003 Correspondence G-L (Box 3)
  - 2003 Correspondence M (Box 3)
  - 2003 Correspondence N-Z (Box 3)
  - Books Bought (Box 3)
  - Books Sold (Box 3)
  - Car (Box 3)
  - Dues and Subscriptions (Box 3)
  - Entertainment (Box 3)
  - Gifts (Box 3)
  - Janitorial (Box 3)
  - Office Equipment (Box 3)
  - Office Supplies (Box 3)
  - Postage (Box 3)
  - Restoration and Framing (Box 3)
  - Repairs (Box 3)
  - Security System (Box 3)
  - Telephone (Box 3)
  - Travel (Box 3)
  - Utilities (Box 3)
  - 2004 Correspondence A-C (Box 4)
  - 2004 Correspondence D-K (Box 4)
  - 2004 Correspondence L-R (Box 4)
  - 2004 Correspondence S-Z (Box 4)
  - Books Sold (Box 4)
  - Books Bought (Box 4)
  - Accounting (Box 4)
  - Advertising (Box 4)
  - Book Fairs (Box 4)
  - Car (Box 4)
  - Dues and Subscriptions (Box 4)
  - Entertainment (Box 4)
  - Internet (Box 4)
  - Janitorial (Box 4)
  - Postage (Box 4)
  - Office Supplies (Box 4)
  - Printing (Box 4)
  - Restoration (Box 4)
  - Security (Box 4)
  - Telephone (Box 4)
  - Travel (Box 4)
  - Utilities (Box 4)
  - 2005 Correspondence A-G (Box 4)
  - 2005 Correspondence H-L (Box 4)
  - 2005 Correspondence M-Q (Box 4)
  - 2005 Correspondence R-Z (Box 4)
  - Books Sold (Box 4)
  - Books Bought (Box 4)
  - Accounting (Box 4)
  - Advertising (Box 4)
  - Book Fairs (Box 4)
  - Business Fairs (Box 4)
  - Car (Box 4)
  - Dues and Subscriptions (Box 4)
  - Gifts (Box 4)
  - Internet (Box 4)
  - Janitorial (Box 4)
  - Office (Box 4)
  - Postage (Box 4)
  - Painting (Box 4)
  - Repairs (Box 4)
  - Restoration (Box 4)
  - Telephone (Box 4)
  - Travel (Box 4)
  - Utilities (Box 4)
  - Correspondence 2006 (Box 5)
  - Books Bought (Box 5)
  - Accounting (Box 5)
  - Advertising (Box 5)
  - Car (Box 5)
  - Dues and Subscriptions (Box 5)
  - Entertainment (Box 5)
  - Book Fairs (Box 5)
  - Gifts (Box 5)
  - Internet (Box 5)
  - Janitorial (Box 5)
  - Office Supplies (Box 5)
  - Postage (Box 5)
  - Printing (Box 5)
  - Repairs (Box 5)
  - Restoration (Box 5)
  - Telephone (Box 5)
  - Travel (Box 5)
  - Utilities (Box 5)
  - Correspondence 2007 (Box 5)
  - Books Bought (Box 5)
  - Business Documents (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - Accounting (Box 5)
  - Advertising (Box 5)
  - Book Fairs (Box 5)
  - Internet (Box 5)
  - Office Supplies (Box 5)
  - Printing (Box 5)
  - Restoration (Box 5)
  - Telephone (Box 5)
  - Utilities (Box 5)
  - Welty, Eudora., 1980-1988 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence., 1973-1980 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence., 1981-1982 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence., 1983 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence., 1984-1985 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence., 1986-1987 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence., 1988 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence., 1989 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence., 1990 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence., 1991, Jan.-July (Box 6)
  - Correspondence., 1991, Aug.-Dec. (Box 6)
  - Correspondence., 1992 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence., 1993 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence., 1994 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence., 1995 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence., 1996, Jan.-Apr. (Box 6)
  - Correspondence., 1996, May-Dec. (Box 6)
  - Correspondence. (3 folders), 2011 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence. A-G. Undated (Box 6)
  - Correspondence. H-Z. Undated (Box 6)
  - Reviews. (2 folders), 1974-1996 (Box 6)
  - "Addeds.", 2001-2005 (Box 6)
  - Photographs (Box 6)
  - Accounting (Box 6)
  - Advertising (Box 6)
  - Book Fairs (Box 6)
  - Business Taxes (Box 6)
  - Car (Box 6)
  - Dues and Subscriptions (Box 6)
  - Gifts (Box 6)
  - Internet (Box 6)
  - Janitorial (Box 6)
  - Office Supplies (Box 6)
  - Postage (Box 6)
  - Painting (Box 6)
  - Repairs (Box 6)
  - Restoration (Box 6)
  - Telephone (Box 6)
  - Travel (Box 6)
  - Utilities (Box 6)
  - Books Sold (Box 6)
  - Books Bought (Box 6)
  - Correspondence., 2001-2008 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence., 2003-2010 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence. (2 folders), 2009-2010 (Box 7)
  - Books Bought (Box 7)
  - Books Sold (Box 7)
  - Accounting (Box 7)
  - Advertising (Box 7)
  - Book Fairs (Box 7)
  - Business Tax (Box 7)
  - Dues and Subscriptions (Box 7)
  - Gifts (Box 7)
  - Insurance (Box 7)
  - Internet (Box 7)
  - Janitorial (Box 7)
  - Office Supplies (Box 7)
  - Postage (Box 7)
  - Painting (Box 7)
  - Repairs (Box 7)
  - Restoration (Box 7)
  - Telephone (Box 7)
  - Utilities (Box 7)
  - Selected Book Reviews (Box 7)
  - Books Bought (Box 7)
  - Books Sold (Box 7)
  - Accounting (Box 7)
  - Advertising (Box 7)
  - Book Fairs (Box 7)
  - Business Taxes (Box 7)
  - Car (Box 7)
  - Gifts (Box 7)
  - Insurance (Box 7)
  - Internet (Box 7)
  - Office Supplies (Box 7)
  - Postage (Box 7)
  - Painting (Box 7)
  - Repairs (Box 7)
  - Restoration (Box 7)
  - Telephone (Box 7)
  - Travel (Box 7)
  - Utilities (Box 7)
  - Correspondence. (3 folders), 2009 (Box 8)
  - Travel (Box 8)
  - Telephone (Box 8)
  - Restoration (Box 8)
  - Repairs (Box 8)
  - Painting (Box 8)
  - Postage (Box 8)
  - Office Supplies (Box 8)
  - Internet (Box 8)
  - Janitorial (Box 8)
  - Office Equipment (Box 8)
  - Insurance (Box 8)
  - Gifts (Box 8)
  - Dues and Subscriptions (Box 8)
  - Car (Box 8)
  - Book Fairs (Box 8)
  - Advertising (Box 8)
  - Accounting (Box 8)
  - Books Bought (Box 8)
  - Books Sold (Box 8)
  - Correspondence. A-H., 2012 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence. I-L., 2012 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence. M-Z., 2012 (Box 8)
  - Postage (Box 8)
  - Telephone (Box 8)
  - Advertising (Box 8)
  - Internet (Box 8)
  - Dues and Subscriptions (Box 8)
  - Car (Box 8)
  - Book Purchases (Box 8)
  - Restoration (Box 8)
  - Book Sales (Box 8)
  - Office Supplies (Box 8)
  - Correspondence and Accompanying Materials (Box 9)
    - Holiday Cards (Box 9)
    - A-Z (33 folders) (Box 9)
  - Business Records (Box 10)
    - A-Z (42 folders) (Box 10)
  - Invoices (2 binding cases) (Box 11)
  - Invoices (2 binding cases) (Box 12)
  - Invoices (2 binding cases) (Box 13)
  - Invoices (2 binding cases) (Box 14)
  - Invoices (2 binding cases) (Box 15)
  - Invoices (2 binding cases) (Box 16)
  - Correspondence. A-C., 2013 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence. D-F., 2013 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence. G-H., 2013 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence. J-L., 2013 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence. M-P., 2013 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence. R-S., 2013 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence. T-Z., 2013 (Box 17)
  - Accounting (Box 17)
  - Advertising (Box 17)
  - Book Fairs (Box 17)
  - Business Tax (Box 17)
  - Dues and Subscriptions (Box 17)
  - Gifts (Box 17)
  - Insurance (Box 17)
  - Internet (Box 17)
  - Janitorial (Box 17)
  - Office Supplies (Box 17)
  - Postage (Box 17)
  - Painting (Box 17)
  - Repairs (Box 17)
  - Restoration (Box 17)
  - Travel (Box 17)
  - Books Sold (Box 17)
  - Books Bought (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 17)
  - Correspondence: Tan, Amy (Box 18)
  - Correspondence: Yellin, Herb (Box 18)
  - Correspondence: A-D (Box 18)
  - Correspondence: E-L (Box 18)
  - Correspondence: M-R (Box 18)
  - Correspondence: S-Z (Box 18)
  - Invoices (Box 18)
  - Books Bought (Box 18)
  - Accounting (Box 18)
  - Advertising (Box 18)
  - Book Fairs (Box 18)
  - Business Taxes (Box 18)
  - Dues and Subscriptions (Box 18)
  - Gifts (Box 18)
  - Insurance (Box 18)
  - Internet (Box 18)
  - Medical (Box 18)
  - Office Supplies (Box 18)
  - Postage (Box 18)
  - Painting (Box 18)
  - Repairs (Box 18)
  - Restoration (Box 18)
  - Telephone (Box 18)
  - Travel (Box 18)
  - Utilities (Box 18)
  - Accounting papers (Box 18)
  - Entertainment receipts (Box 18)
  - Correspondence and receipts (Box 18)
  - Correspondence, bills, and receipts (Box 18)
  - Repair bills and receipts (Box 18)
  - Book fair forms and receipts (Box 18)
  - Business taxes (Box 18)
  - Car receipts (Box 18)
  - Printing receipts (Box 18)
  - Janitorial receipts (Box 18)
  - Office supply bills and receipts (Box 18)
  - Invoices (Box 18)
  - Verizon phone bills (Box 18)
  - Travel receipts and bills (Box 18)
  - Dues and subscriptions (Box 18)
  - Utilities (Box 18)
  - IPostage (Box 19)
  - Book purchase (Box 19)
  - Paid invoices (Box 19)
  - Correspondence, (5 folders) (Box 19)
  - Inward Journey/Ross Macdonald manuscript materials, edited by Ralph B. Sipper (Box No Box)
- 2022 Additions
  - Correspondence, 2021 (Box 19)
  - Correspondence, 2020 (Box 19)
  - "Who Said That?" - pamphlet, 2014 (Box 19)
- 2023 Additions
  - Correspondence, 2022; 3 Folders (Box 19)